this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Roberto De Cosmo your bio is
very impressive Roberto I'm only going
to mention a very small part of it so
apologies in advance Roberto has a PHD
in computer science from the University
of Pisa he was an associate professor
for almost a decade at a call from our
Supreme Paris you can correct me on that
and in 1999 you became a computer
science full professor at the University
Harris Detroit I think the first school
is it called normal Superior the
university is now University of Paris
City but well thank you perfect Roberto
is a long-term free software Advocate
contributing to its adoption since 1998
with the best seller hacking the world
running seminars writing articles and
creating free software itself he created
in 2015 and now directs software
Heritage an initiative to build the
universal Archive of all the source code
publicly available in partnership with
UNESCO Roberto welcome to software
engineering radio obviously I've trimmed
your bio but is there anything that I
missed that I should have highlighted
well no I can just sum up on them if you
want my life is very three lines I mean
30 plus years doing research and
education in computer science equatorial
surgery advocating about free software
and the users free software weight and
the last 10 to 15 years it was just
trying to to lend the hand in building
infrastructure for the common good and
software activities the main work at my
hand today thank you perfect so for the
listeners today we're going to
understand what software Heritage is
software Heritage sorry just a small
disclaimer I'm a software Heritage
Ambassador so that means I volunteer to
get the message across so we're going to
talk about what software Heritage is
we're going to discuss some of the
issues around storing and retrieving
this data at global scale and then we're
going to finish off the show talking
about software Heritage IDs and where
they come in and what they are so let's
get cracking so software Heritage
Roberto what is it well okay to put it
in a nutshell
something we are trying to build to
build at the same time a Library of
Alexandria of source code I mean a place
where you can find the source code of
all public available software developed
in the world no matter where it has been
developed or how by whom and at the same
time in Revolution infrastructure at the
service of different kind of needs the
needs of cultural heritage preservation
because software is part of our cultural
Health it need to be preserved it is a
necessary infrastructure for open
science in Academia that needs a place
where to store the software used for
doing research and to ensure
reproducibility of result it is a tool
for industry that needs to have a
reference repository all the components
or software which are used today and it
is also at the service of public
administration that in the place where
safe restoring and showing the software
that is used in handling cities and data
for example for a transparency and
accountability so in a nutshell
tradition is trying to address all these
issues with one single infrastructure
when we talk about publicly available
software it's just typically things that
would be on GitHub or gitlab or any of
the other free open source git
repositories or is it just is it not
limited to git yeah the the ambition of
so tragedy actually to collect the
elderly peace of public available
software source code no matter where it
is developed so of course we are hiding
everything that is publicly available on
GitHub or GitHub but we are going much
broader than that so we are going after
tiny small forges distributed all around
the world and we are going after package
managers we are going after distribution
the share software there are so many
different places where software is
developed and distributed and we
actually try to collect it from all
these places in some sense when
infrastructure to bring them all in the
same place and give you access to
Mankind's software in a single place
thank you so if you didn't do this what
problems arise here very good question
so what why did we decided to start this
initiative we need to go back seven
years ago when this was started we were
doing in our group here some research
search on how to analyze open source
software finding vulnerabilities or
quality Etc so the question goes uh it's
a moment say okay let's see it would be
able for for example to scale some
software analysis tools at the level or
the public available software and when
you start discussing about this you say
okay but where do we get all the public
available software so we started looking
around and we discovered that we as
everybody else we are just assuming the
software was also safely available in
archived and maintained on our public
charges like tutorials or Google code or
bitbucket or GitHub or GitHub or other
places like this remember seven years
ago and then we realized that actually
no one of these places were actually in
archive on any collaborative development
platform you can create a project you
can work on it you can erase a project
you can rename it you can move it
elsewhere so there is no guarantee that
tomorrow you will see the same thing as
today because somebody can remove things
and then it 2015 we had this incredible
shock of seeing very large at the moment
very popular code hosting platform
shutting down it was a case of Google
code there where there were more than
700 000 projects it was a case of
guitarus there were 120 000 projects
then later on remember 2019 be back at
Phase it out support for the Mercurial
version control system and that was a
quarter of a medium project unplug it
you see the point so what happens here
is somebody by clicking a finger can
remove hundreds of thousands of projects
from the web from the internet who takes
care of making sure the server is not
lost that it is preserved that it is
maintained for people that need to reuse
it or to understand it later on and so
these were the core motivation of our
mission making sure we do not lose the
pressure software that is part of our
technological revolution in our cultural
so motivation number one being an
archive in some sense without an archive
you take a risk of actually losing an
incredible amount of significant part of
our technology today thank you and was
there other things that you explored for
example like the Wayback machine is it
something they were interested in
helping with or did you just think we
have to do this ourselves yeah very good
question because we are kind of software
Engineers here so the the good point is
kind of Twitter and then the wheel okay
if there is already a will try to use it
so we we went around if we look at the
different initiatives that were involved
in some sort of digital preservation so
of course there are archives for
maintaining videos for maintaining
audios for maintaining books for example
internet access is an incredible job for
actually archiving the web and then you
have people that maintain archival video
games for example or people that
maintain some type of disintables but
looking around we found nobody actually
doing anything about preserving the
source code or sorted not just the
binaries not just running a software but
actually understanding how it is built
nobody was doing this and so that was
the reason why we decided to start a
specific operation whose goal is to
actually go out collect fresh air and
share the source code of software not
the web pages this is internet archive
not the mailing list you have initiative
like Gmail that is not a virtual machine
you have other people doing this the
source code only the source code but
over the source code and that was our
original Mission and the mission we are
trying to pursue today thank you and as
the only open source free software that
you archive you mentioned operating
systems and well actually no the point
of the archive is to collect everything
which is publicly available which is
much broader than just open source
software and free software and these are
some consequences for example if you
come to the archive and you visit the
content of the academy you can find a
piece of software but the fact that it
is a cut in software doesn't mean that
it is open source you can use it as you
want you need to go and look at the
license Associated to the center some is
just made available publicly but you
cannot use it for commercial use some is
open source actually a lot is open
source luckily our Point as an archive
is making sure we do not lose something
which is precious and valuable that has
been made public at the moment in time
independently on the license it is
attached away then the people visiting
their car even if it is not open sour
they can still read it they can
understand what is going on they can
still look at the story or what is going
on so there is value even if you are not
allowed by the license to fully reuse it
adapt it as you want interesting thank
you and how does this archive look what
what does it look like is it portal into
different mirrors of these places or you
know what other particular features that
you offer that are attractive to use
once something's archived very good
question so when we started this it was
a a lot of thought going into well how
should we design the architecture of
this thing so how do we get the software
in how do we store it how do we present
it how do we make it available for
people for views and then we Face the
some very tough initial difficulties
because when you want to Archive
software that is stored on GitHub or
stored on GitHub or stored in the Debian
or Ubuntu distribution of any package
manager like PayPal or npm or any other
places like this volume there are
thousands of them unfortunately there is
no standard there is no standard just to
to list the content of the repository
like on GitHub you need to plug into the
guitar tuning field which is not the
same as the gitlab event feed which is
not the same as a bit packet and so it
which is pretty different to the way you
can request the Ubuntu distribution to
give you the list over the source
packages which is a different way of
interacting with npm okay right you see
the quantities where it's a bubble Tower
here so we need to build adapters to
restore this contents and then the
complexity still is there because even
even when we have the list of all the
project then this project are maintained
in different ways so some projects are
developed using git other developer
using subversion rw's Mercury I mean
different version control system then
the package formats are not the same are
pretty different so the the challenge
was how should we go I mean how how
would you I mean when we were listening
how would you go about preserving this
on their long-term so the the Apparently
easy choice would be to say well okay I
make a dump of the git repository a damp
for the subversion repository I keep it
and then when somebody wants to read it
they run guitar they run subduction or
they run Mercury or some other two on
this particular dump the treatment thing
but this is a very fragile approach
because then what direction of the tool
are you gonna use in five years or 10
years to reduce Etc it's complicated so
we decided to go the extra mile
into this work for you so actually we
run these adapters we decode or the
history of development we decode the
package format and then we embed all
these in a single gigantic data
structure that keeps all the software
and all the history of developing in a
standard uniform format which we will
probably spend a little more time later
on in the in this conversation but just
to to make the point clear I mean it is
not an easy fit and the advantage is
that now when you go to the archive you
go to archive.j.com you you end on a
very simple landing page that has just a
one simple line where like Google okay
you type in what you are looking for and
this allows you to look through
180 million archived projects actually
not inside the source code you are
searching in the URLs of the project
that you archive and when you find one
project that is interesting to you it
doesn't matter if it was from git or
from subduction from akulia from GitHub
for pocket Etc everything is presented
in the same uniform way which is very
familiar to a developer because it is
designed by Developers for developers so
it gives you access to possibility of
visiting navigating inside the source
code seeing all the Version Control
history
identifying every single place of the
software there so thank you forge like a
contrasting platform but it is an
archive uniform independent on where the
software comes from so just to summarize
that so I can understand that I've got
got this correct in my head so all the
different places you archive you're not
mirroring you're archiving it so you
mentioned npm you mentioned other packet
managers different Source control
projects like gets version which could
live on gitlab GitHub guitarists all
these types of ones it's not as if they
all have an FTP access point to get in
and get the software you might have a
read-only view through a web browser
through https you might then have to use
the get tools or the conversion tools to
get the actual source code out that
you're interested in to Archive so you
mentioned that you've developed adapters
to pull them all in and then effectively
create kind of like a DSL domain
specific language to get all that data
in a format that you can work with that
is more agnostic and isn't reliant on
the different versions of tools or that
would need to change over the next five
to ten years was that good summary or a
bad summary no it's it's a pretty good
summary the idea is actually you know
our first driver was how to make sure we
can preserve everything needed for the
developer in 20 years for example to
restore or his or her laptop or whatever
will be instead without putting 20 years
at the exact state of a software project
source code as it was at a given moment
in time so you can work on it and so the
best approach was exactly as you
described to to do this conversion in a
uniform data starch now which is simple
well documented and that will be
possible to use later on but
independently of the Future tools that
will be developed or outdated or
forgotten did any sort of Standards come
out of this work that would help other
people so I've been adoption of the
techniques that you've created yes
basically for people who use uh tools
like kit you can think of their
that keeps them further and so there we
needed one standard and this standard is
a the standard of the identifier that
are attached to all the nodes of this
particular graph this identifies that
you can use today to pinpoint the
particular file
directory or repository or version could
mean to reduce you are interested in and
making sure that nobody can tamper with
it so you have integrity guarantees you
have permanent persistence guarantees
and these are the sort of Heritage
identifiers on which we will spend a
little bit more time or later on in the
conversation so this is a needed
standard in the work on standardization
is starting right now we hope to see
this helping our colleagues and federal
engineers
have a better mechanism to track the
evolution of the software across the
Fuller software supply chain in the
future yes we're going to chat about in
the last section of the show about the
the IDS that you've referenced there
okay so I'm going to move us on to the
middle part of the show we're going to
talk about storing all this data and
retrieving it at a global scale because
obviously it's a ton of data so my first
question is going to be what sort of
scale and data volumes are we talking
about and obviously that changes every
day every minute absolutely indeed if
you go to the main webpage of the
archive which is
archive.soft.org you will see a few
diagrams that show you how the archive
has evolved over time so today we have
indexeded more than 180 million projects
I mean Origins I mean places in the web
where you can find projects and this
plays down to over 12 billion unique
source code files so 12 billion source
code file looks like a lot but actually
remember these are unique files so if
the same file is used in 1000 different
projects but we continue only one so we
keep it only once and then we remember
where it comes from and it also contains
a little bit more of two and a half
billion revisions different versions or
status of development of a particular a
software project this is huge the
overall storage that we need to keep all
this you know it depends on how you look
at it it is one petabyte today more or
less so one petabyte is big for me if I
want to put it on my laptop it is too
big it is pretty tiny when you compare
to what Google or Amazon need to have in
their data service or data center of
course at the same time having one
petabyte which is composed of 12 billion
very small and tiny little pieces of
source code poses significant challenges
when you want to actually develop an
efficient storage system to keep all
this data over time and then if you look
at the graph I mean not just the price
but all the directories the commits the
revision the releases the snapshot it
all the other pieces that are in the
graph with all these things that say
inside this directory this particular
file content is called
include.age but in this other directory
the same content is called something
else dot C all this graph is today 25
billion nodes and
350 billion edges and so where do you
store such a graph because you could
imagine you can use some graph oriented
database but graph oriented database for
these size of graphs which have specific
topologies are not easy to build where
do you store this how do you store this
all this in in a way that is efficient
to write because our first object is
being an archive so we need to be able
to write quickly at the same time also
efficient to read because it's a moment
when everybody is going to use the
software user we will need to face an
increasing Demand Being able to provide
result efficiently quickly so to people
that want to visit and browse the
archive so these are big big challenges
obviously this isn't done for free what
sort of costs are we talking about here
and how do you fund this project
yeah indeed that's a big question so
when you start something like this
so when we start this on seven years
they go out and there was a significant
time we spent on thinking about how
would you
go about building such an infrastructure
in a sustainable way so there are very
different possibilities because I mean
there is a cost of course imagine just
just running the data center and and if
you look in our web page today you will
see all the member of the team we are 15
people full time on the project right
now okay
of course it is not as big as a large
company but it is pretty significant in
terms of course you cannot just do it on
your free time obviously volunteer it
requires significant funding to keep it
handy so the possibility number one
would have been to create a private
company okay it's a kind of stacked up
and try to raise funding to sell
services to particular stakeholders but
you will remember 2015 we saw Google
code shutting down and guitar use which
was another popular Forge back then
shutting down after an acquisition baby
Club then this summer we have seen
gitlab more or less was considering
removing all the projects that were
inactive for more than a year going into
the business space for such kind of an
infrastructure was not the right
approach okay we have seen I mean for
different reasons which are pretty
legitimate making money or satisfying
your stakeholders or stock call this
companies may decide to switch off or to
change the service they provide so you
didn't want to go that direction so the
point was to actually create a
non-profit multi-stakeholder their
international organization with a
precise objective of collecting
preserving and sharing the source code
or creating maintaining this archive and
this is the reason why we had this
agreement we signed an agreement in 2017
with UNESCO which is a United Nation
educational scientific and cultural
organization and the reason why we
started going around and looking for
sponsors and members and so basically
project is run today by using many of
the accounts from some 20 different
organizations that can be companies can
be academias can be universities can be
Ministries or in different countries
that provide some money in form of a
membership
to the organization in exchange for the
service that organization provides to
follow the stakeholders so this path we
are trying to follow it has been a long
time in seven years we moved from zero
supporters to 20 which is uh not bad but
we are pretty far from the number that
we need to have a stable organization in
the long term and we need help in going
into that direction to separate Global
project which matches the goals you're
trying to achieve absolutely thank you
so I'm going to dig into the storage
layer now we'll touch upon I think in
the software Heritage ID section about
the the graph protocol or the graph work
that you've done as well because you did
just mention that briefly
so how frequently do you archive this
data how many nodes do you have well if
you look um if some of our listeners
here is curious if you go to
docs.soft range.org and one of the first
links in there brings you to a nice web
page that describes and other old
architecture I mean the architecture it
was used up to a few months ago so how
would you go about archiving everything
which is out there they we actually have
three ways of doing this one is a
regular and automated calling or some
sources where the sources are not all
equal they do not have the same
throughput of course so you have much
more activity on GitHub than on small
local code hosting platform that has
just a few hundreds of projects for it
it is not the same activity of course so
what we do is we regularly grow these
places we do not archive all those on
GitHub as soon as you make a commit to
it it could be technically would be
possible right I could listen to the
event
feed from the cabin every time somebody
makes a commit I could immediately
trigger an archival that this is just
not technically doable with the
resources we have today so we have a
different approach so we regularly lift
this every few months the full contents
of GitHub we put in the queue of project
that needs to be archived all the
projects have been changed over the
lapse of time to project it didn't
change we did not have them again of
course and then we go through all these
backdogs slowly but then this is a
regular way then the other solution that
we have put in place is a mechanism that
is called save code now so imagine that
you find that there is a project that is
important to Archive today not in three
months when it goes around the top of
the encoding queue and then it is
possible for you to go to this
save.softwareitage.org point our columns
to one particular version control system
that is supported and Trigger archival
immediately and then the third
possibility is having an agreement with
some organization or institutional
companies they actually want to regular
archive their software with specific
metadata and quality control and this is
a deposit interface and of course to use
this deposit interface you need to have
a formality limit result for doing that
so I hope this answer a little bit the
question so regular trolling that is not
as quick as you could imagine but also
mechanisms for you to bypass this queue
and just say hey please do so save this
now because it is important right now or
another mechanism that allows people to
actually put content into the archive
then we need to trust the people that do
this we need an agreement with them so
do you regularly hit API limits with the
big guys like GitHub gitlab or do you
have to contact them and say this is
what we're doing can you give us some
type of special yes indeed and so for
example we are very happy that we
managed to sign an agreement with GitHub
in 2019 November 2019 and the object of
this agreement was exactly to have a
specific elements in the API that they
actually provide us to something to
simplify the archival process and to
have some great limit raised through our
own code that why is a typical thing
that people do when they do it without
saying anything to anybody they just I
mean bypass a limitation by spawning
tons of clients of different tokens Etc
but we would like not to do this we
prefer to have a direct support from in
direct contact with the forges that
consider that we have a small
organization so setting up an agreement
with all possible forges around the
world is not something we can do in just
we would like to but have not able to do
so we made designing the biggest one
which is Ethan and we do not have
agreement with the others but we would
love to have an agreement with
github.com or with the bucket etc for
the moment we managed to call them
without hitting too many range limits
but it would be better if this could be
written down in an agreement yeah I'd
imagine that we're doing something on
the back end somewhere with these big
guys in the countries where they have
most of their storage and you mentioned
anyone can submit data so you've got
save.softwareheritage.org I'll put these
links in the show notes anyway and then
the main archive one I think I added my
own personal source project to it and
it's there did I miss any of the entry
points
now then just a little extra information
on Silicon now when you trigger the
archive of the project that is on a
platform that we know then it goes
immediately in the archival queue in
this quicker fast lane Fast Track if you
want but if it comes from a platform
never heard of I mean food.bard said
something this goes into a waiting queue
where one of our team members regularly
looked to check that it is actually not
the copy of some or no videos somewhere
you know I mean something we try to
check a little bit what people submit
but once it is better then it goes in
that's another question about verifying
data okay you mentioned before a sort of
five to ten year or 20 year timeline
you're trying to preserve things for
what sort of realistic do you think well
first of all as you know we we don't
know if you tomorrow we will be alive
but the point is that we really try to
set up or the design of everything we do
has been thought out in such a way of
maximizing the chances that this
preservation effort will last as long as
possible
so this means different things for
example all the infrastructure
absolutely every
angle line of source code of Our Own
infrastructure in software engine is
free sorter or uses free sort and opens
result why because otherwise you you
could not test us or preserving a long
time if you we use proprietary
components on which we have no control
and then nobody could replicate if
needed that is one point the other point
the organization again thought has a
non-profit non-term Foundation trying to
maintain it over time but then there
have also technical challenges how can
we be sure that this data will not be
lost as a moment in time because imagine
some of us in the team makes a mistakes
and erases of the data in one of the
servers or we get hacked or there is a
fire in one of the data centers or women
many differences over or it has happened
some legislation is passed that actually
endangers the mission of reservation how
do we prevent this because if you want
to last 10 20 100 years these have
already challenges you need to seriously
take into account and soon to avoid the
danger which are more technical our
approach today is to actually have
replication and all over the place so we
had a mirror program in place a mirror
is a full copy of the archive maintained
by any other organization in another
country potentially on another
Technology stock in such a way that if
something happens to the main node the
mirror nodes can take up from there and
all the data is preserved you see this
is one possibility and but this mirror
program has also the advantage of
protecting a bit from this potentially
legal challenge because imagine tomorrow
there is a directive actually let me
tell the real story so a few years ago
here in Europe we had a change in
copyright flow through direct your
European commission that made a lot of
noise back then what people probably
don't know he said one tiny provision in
this directive endangered or the code
hosting platform for open source
massively and so it took us in
collaboration with many other people
from another organizations from free
software organization of resource
organization from companies like
to spend in an inordinate amount of time
to have a change into this legislation
this directly to actually protect open
source software and protect platforms
like GitHub on one side but also
archives like hours or distribution like
Debian this has been kind of a notice
and because it is just software and not
I mean videos images culture Etc in the
old discussions but it was a real real
challenge in danger so imagine it
happens again in another moment in time
then it is important to have copies of
their type under other jurisdiction that
will be protected from this kind of
Provisions so this is the way we try to
minimize the risk of failing over time
yeah that's a very good point because at
the point of archive or mirror if it's
legal when it changes it's only
restricted by that part of the world and
the laws there so if if we dig into
generic storage lots of us are involved
with data centers or network attack
stores that type of things and we know
the rule of thumb where storage devices
fail generally around every three years
or so my question was how do you handle
this but I think you've just explained
that by the master nodes and the mirror
nodes is that correct and actually the
Mirror Mirror node is a kind of an
extreme solution to the issue of course
inside our maybe we can I can tell you a
little bit more about what is going Down
Under the Hoon today we actually have
three copies of the archive under our
own control so not on the mirrors one
copy is fully on our bare iron that we
have in our own data center hosted by
the area organization says and then we
have two full copies one on Azure which
is sponsored by Microsoft and one on AWS
which is gracefully provided by Amazon
so you see we are separating things on
we have backups and and checks I mean
whatever on our own infrastructure but
we also have a full copy on Amazon it
does the same in with different
technology in Nigeria that does the same
with different Technologies so of course
nothing is fully safe but we believe
this particular setting today is a
relatively rare assuring okay to against
I mean losing data by corruption on the
disk we also have some tools that runs
regularly on the archive to check
Integrity it is called swhs Hardware but
I mean it goes over there the disc can
check things happen and the extra point
which is interesting for us is that
we'll be going to this later on again
using these identifiers that we use that
are used all over the architecture which
are cryptographic identifiers actually
each identifier is a very strong check
some of the contents so it's pretty easy
to navigate the graphing then verify
that there was no corrupture in the data
at every level at every single note we
can do this and then if there is a good
option then we need to go to one of the
other copies and restore the original
object so you're constantly verifying
validating your own backups and your
your own archive you mentioned you as a
very good model which a lot of people
that use the cloud try to do but
sometimes costs get in the way EG having
multiple Cloud providers you know
duplicating that way so you said you've
got your own bare metal in your own data
centers then you've got a zero and
you've got AWS yeah AWS so if you wrote
metal just because I'm interested I
really like to know it's absolutely
what's our file system do you run you
know is it a raid system said FR sorry
all that type of stuff yeah okay what
they can describe to you is a current
architecture that we are changing all
this I mean moving tomorrow resilient
Solutions so the the current
architecture was based on two different
things one thing is where do you store
the file contents okay well the blocks
the binary objects that contained it in
the inside contents and the other part
is where do you store the rest of the
graph I mean the internal nodes and the
relationships now for the file contents
it is 12 billion and Counting five
contents we use an object storage and
this object storage was you remember our
constraint is that you we decided only
to use in our own infrastructure open
source software okay so I cannot use
solution which are proprietary or behind
behind closet doors unfortunately when
we started this the only thing that we
managed to make run was using a ZFS
phase system with a two-letter sharping
on the hashes of the contrast this is a
poor man object storage right and it is
not particularly inefficient in Reading
it's not necessarily particularly
efficient in writing but it was simple
clean could be used now we are hitting
the mutation in this kind of thing
because it is too slow for example to
replicate data in another mirror Etc and
there we are moving slowly to another
solution that is using self which is
very well known as a notch storage it is
open source it's actually pretty well
maintained by an active Community it has
a bucket by redart Etc so it seems nice
the only point is that this kind of
object storages are usually designed to
Archive very large object larger weight
I mean 64 kilobytes okay objects the
optimized for this kind of size when you
are storing source code half of our file
contents are less than three kilobytes
there are some that are just a few
hundred bytes and so there is a problem
if you just use a bear safe solution to
Archive this because you have you have
what is called a storage expansion for
example to store one petabyte you need
much more than one petabyte because of
the block size Etc
so now we have been working with experts
in in safe that we collaborate with from
a company called Easter eggs and we
support from without people in
themselves to actually develop a thin
layer on top of self that allows us to
use self-efficiently so it's a very well
known very well maintained open source
object storage but add these extra
layers that make it okay for our
particular workload shape which is
different from things that our friends
listeners probably have to handle that
for the storage then for the storage of
the object the object storage then if
you look at the graph again for the
graph when we started we used postgres
as a database to store graph information
as many as you will know I mean a
relational database is not the best
solution when you have graphs and you
need to Travelers graphs of course but
it is reliable has transactions will
ensure that we didn't lose the data over
time
and now we are slowly moving to another
solution that will be more efficient in
how they are seeing the graph data we
have developed a new technology that is
not yet visible will be visible I hope
next year that allowed to Traverse the
graph efficiently without hitting the
limit of SQL approaches but you see I
mean complexity of this task is also on
the technology side when we engage in
only using open source component that we
can actually understand and use we are
rising the path of what we need to do to
actually make all this work so just to
summarize that we started off with
Z over ZFS on your own bare metal I'm
not sure what AWS are sure we'll be
doing then you've hit the limitations of
that and you've moved to Surf is that
CEF or c-e-p-h it is c-e-p-h yeah that's
what I thought I'll put I'll put a link
in and you're working with the vendors
and all the open source experts to make
that specific to your use case so that's
for the actual files and you only store
one instance of a file because you check
the contents of it so there's no
duplication and the graph what sort of
graph are we talking about is that how
to relate those binary blobs to metadata
or no actually you know when you look at
your file system any usual place system
display system you have a director
inside the directory and other
directories you have files etc etc so if
you look at the picture representation
of this system it's actually a tree user
directory tree but actually it is more
than a three it is a graph because there
are some nodes that are shared at some
moment okay you have the same director
that appears in two other directories
and with the same name so technically it
is a graph is more than a tree so this
is actually the graph we are talking
about so the representation of the
structure of the file system the
correspond to a particular status of the
development of a source code plus the
other nodes and links that correspond to
the different phases of the evolution
every time you mark a version release
the Commit This adds a node to the graph
Point into the status of the source code
in the particular moment that is this
directory see so this is a graph we are
talking about well I did a share on B
plus 3 data structures which we spoke
about graphs and things like I'll put a
link into the show notes for that and we
also did a show quite a few years ago
now back in 2017 with James cowling on
dropbox's distributed storage systems
there might be some good crossovers
there okay so the graph that you're
talking about I I think during my
research is it's a Markle graph is that
correct yes this is a solution we
decided to adopt or Sunday to represent
all these dfm projects and to make sure
we can scale up with respect to the
modern approach of development where
every time you want to contribute to a
project today you start by making a copy
locally on your space and then you add a
modification then you make a pool or
merge or Acosta Etc so that means that
for example if you look on guitar
thousands of copies of the Linux scale
so archiving each of them separately
from the other would be silly we are
using a space in an unefficient way so
what we do we build this graph is a
miracle graph we will go on to the
details a little bit data that actually
has a ability to spot when two file
contents are the same when two
directories are identical when two
commits are actually the same and by
using these properties using this
cryptographic identifier the spot
exactly that allows you to supportive a
part of the graph is a copy of another
part of the graph we actually managed to
compress and they duplicate everything
at all the levels so if a file is used
in different projects we keep it only
once but if a directory a real directory
that may contain 10 000 files is the
same in three different projects on
guitar we keep it only once and we just
remember whether it has been present in
this and that and that other project and
all the way up by doing this according
to statistics we made a few years ago so
it takes time to compute the statistics
we do not do it every time we had a fact
of of compression of 300 okay so instead
of 300 petabyte we have only one
petabyte by avoiding copying and
duplicating the same fine or the same
directory over and again every time
somebody makes a follower another copy
somewhere else in the on the planet I
suppose it's a very similar analogy to
creating a zip file it removes all that
duplication and compression in some
sense but in one sense it is less
intelligent than a zip file because in a
zip file you look for similarities when
here we are we are happy with identical
content so we we duplicate only when
something is identical to something else
it could be nice it will be interesting
to push edit further and say hey but
there are many file setups similar one
to the other even if they are not
identical could we compress them among
them and gain space
and the answer is probably yes but
involves another technological layer
that will take time and resources to
develop perfect thank you that's a good
place to move us on to the last part of
the show we've mentioned these terms
quite a few times so it'd be good to
finish this off when you build the graph
and when you take the binary data or the
blob of data you then have to validate
whether it's changed or whether you need
to go and archive things like that and I
think this is where the cryptographic
hashes for long-term preservation
otherwise known as the software Heritage
ID comes in is that correct yes
absolutely we swh IDs or software ad and
we we just call them Suite in some if
you want to pronounce it quickly I came
across in my research a blog post in
2020 about you exploring and presenting
what an intrinsic ideas versus an
extrinsic ID and and where the swedes or
the swh ID fits in could you spend a
couple of minutes on explaining the
difference between an intrinsic ID and
an extrinsicity oh absolutely and this
is a very interesting point you know
when you need to identify something I
mean an object a concept Etc we have
been used for ages much earlier than the
computer science was born to actually
decide to use some kind of identifiers
so for example you think about your
passport number that is an identifier
sequence of letters and number is an
identifier of U that is used by the
government to check that you have the
right to correspondence for example how
does it actually work but at some moment
in time and you go and see somebody you
say I'm here and they give you a number
which is actually put in a register in a
central register maintained by an
authority and this Center register says
oh this passport number which is a
number here corresponds to this person
the person is a name the the last name
birthplace and all other biometric
potentially relevant information that
are stored in them why we call this
identifier extrinsic because this
identifier has nothing to do I mean your
passport number have nothing to do with
you except the fact that there is a
register somewhere that says this
passport number corresponds to Gabby and
Harry for example in so if some moment
the register disappears or is corrupted
or is manipulated then the link between
the number that identifier that uses a
number the number they choose an
identifier and the object that it
denotes of the person corresponding to
the password number is lost and there is
no way of recovering it in a casting way
I mean yes of course I can read what is
inside the password the password could
be fake right
we have been using extrinsic identifier
for a very very long time so social
security number passport number the
number of member of the local library or
whatever you see whatever but also
before computer science we have been
used to actually use identify the term
better link to the object they are
supposed to be identified maybe one of
the oldest identifier of this kind we
call them intrinsic because identify is
actually in some sense computed from the
object it is intimately related to the
object so one of the oldest of these
things is just a musical notation okay
you agree on a standard you say well
there are any fitting number of musical
notes but for this infinite number
American notes we just agree that there
are eight basic frequencies and the ABC
or Doremi and depending on how you earn
them and then you have the scales and
the pitch and this once you are agree on
this this idea it is pretty easy out of
the sound you can get the identifier in
the out of the netifier you can
reproduce exactly the sound
and similarly in chemistry chemistry we
agreed on a standard on naming things
which are related to the object while we
are talking about sable table chart
then you know it is sodium and this is
NaCl in standard international and
chemical mutation so these are the
difference between extreme Sig
identifier where if you don't have a
register you are dead because there is
no link maintained in intrinsic
identifier where you do not need to
register you just need to agree on the
way you compute identifier from the
object you see so these are the basic
things that are where available even
before computer science now with digital
technology you find extrinsic identifier
in digital system again and when your
login name on GitHub or your user
account or somewhere and this depends on
register but you also find intrinsic
identifier and these are typically this
cryptographic hashes cryptographic
signature all of our listeners are using
daily when they do software development
in a distributed Way by using
distributed Version Control Systems
so I wonder if this is clear enough to
set this stage I'm coming at this moment
in time yeah that was perfect although I
would extrinsic I think like external so
you mentioned you've got the external
register yeah but with the chemical
engineering or chemical sector example
and music there is a third-party
standard that's been agreed that you
potentially need to look up to
understand absolutely which is kind of
like a register well it's more difficult
to corrupt or to lose once you have a
tiny standard you agree upon and that's
okay then everybody agrees but with the
register who maintains a register who
guarantees Integrity of the register who
has control on the register and this for
every single inscription you make there
and also the register is not going to be
public whereas the the way to interpret
the intrinsic ID and that data will be
public because the standard so it's more
protected thank you so let's pull apart
the software Heritage ID the use of
cryptographic hashes and how that backs
off to the Markov graph so we can
understand how changes are mapped
Integrity is protected tamperings proven
not to happen yeah absolutely so let me
start with the preliminary remark I mean
if there are some of our listeners that
are familiar with the plumbing that is
under modern distributed version control
system that is key toward Mercurial Etc
the too long did the read summaries we
are doing exactly the same okay so we
are piggybacking on that particular
approach has been extremely successful
but for some of our decent it actually
never took the time or had the
opportunity to look into the the
plumbing and underline distribution
control system let's explain what what
is going on cover so imagine you need to
represent a status of your you have your
project in front of you okay so you have
a few files a few directories maybe you
made a commitment say okay this is the
status of today how can you identify the
status of your project if you only need
to identify a single file content I mean
that's pretty easy right okay you you
compute the cryptographic checksum for
example you run the comment share one
sum on the file it does some
cryptographic computation and it spits
out a string or a few dozens character
that is a cryptography signature which
is strong it is to say two files which
are physically different infinitely
small chances of getting the same hash
there so you can take this cryptographic
signature as a representation or an
identifier of this particular file
doesn't matter if the file is 2 gigabyte
it represents the identifier is always
show up to this small hash here that's
easy everybody has been doing this for a
long time now the big question is but
what if I want to represent not just a
single file but a full directory this
status of the full directory how can I
do that
but the approach is well let's see what
is in this directory there are many
files okay they have some file name some
properties and I know how to compute the
hash the identifier of these file names
ah so nice idea let me put in a single
text file a representation of the
directory that contains for a nethery
line the name of the file in the hash of
this file in this directory the type of
object are typically a binary object
block but it could be another directory
and the properties and basic properties
of it I put all them one after the
others took them together I sort them in
a standard way this is where we need
agreement like for chemistry I mean how
you solve them well this is a text file
now that represents a directory so on
this particular text file I can compute
the game the same hash okay and the same
command and get the hash now this hash
is a representation is intimately
related to this particular text file
that represents all the other
subcomponents of the directory so if
somebody changes a bit in one of the
many files that are in the directory
then all this construction will produce
a different key a different identifier
so see we are exporting the property of
the cryptographic hash from a single
file to a directory or again if you look
at the original paper of Ralph mercer at
the end of here it is he was describing
an efficient method of computing a hash
of a big chunk of data by using a 3D
representation that's why we call them
Merkel 3 these kind of things okay when
you recompute the hashes on the internal
node by doing this little processor
representing the different components in
the single text file that then you hash
again and you can push this process up
to all the higher level of the graph and
up to the root nodes of the graph and so
for example if you look in the software
Hatchet identifier how they are split up
you have a small prefix that is called
swh let's say okay this is a softwage
identifier then there is a column then
there is a version number because I mean
standards can evolve for the moment we
have one then you have another column
then you have a tag and then say hey
this can identifier of the file content
of a directory of a revision over
release of a snapshot of the food system
using we put the tag it would be not
necessarily needed but it's better to
clarify what you are identify then you
have another corner and then finally you
have this hash which is computed by the
process I just try to describe and I
know it's much better with the in image
but I hope it was clear enough to give
you a gift what is going on and so the
at the end of this story by doing this
procedure in in the graph you are able
to attach to each node or graph a
cryptography identifier that fully
represents the full content of the
subgraph that is rooted there so if
somebody changes anything in the sub
graph the identifier will change this
means that if you get a software
identifier for a Content archived in
software Heritage you store it in a
contact from fresh subcontractor saying
I need you to use this particular
version because I have a security
guarantees or you use it in a research
article to tell your friends if you want
to get the same result you need to get
exactly this where should I see them you
only keep this tiny identifier there
then you go to the assortage archive
with this identifier the software I will
tell you huh you want this directory you
want this community
Etc you extract the source code from
there you can recompute locally by
yourself without no need to trust search
or anybody else the identifier if it
matches it means it is exactly the same
source code in exactly the same
direction so you are safe by using it
right now you see so this is a super big
advantage of using this kind of
identifier and again for our friends
listen today they know something like it
or other things they are used to have
guitars Etc yes it is the same approach
what the difference is that we the way
we compute this identifying software
energy do not depend on the version
control system used by the people who
develop the software given moment in
time if they use it anything so anything
in the archive is index identify exactly
the same way so the big big advantages
that you have in archives or something
that is here we stay there and these
identifiers are trying to identifier a
universal they do not depend on a
particular Version Control System they
apply to other single one of the
contents of the archive thank you that's
a very good summary and just going to
pull some bits apart to get it clear in
my head because I bet the listeners have
the same sort of questions
so you would have a sweat swh ID for
each file each directory and then
potentially the top of the project or
that archive one that encompasses all
those different IDs and the tax file
that you've made another hash off yes
absolutely you have these Federal levels
of the file content the directory
they're releases which correspond to
commit sorry the revision the
corresponder commit the releases and the
snapshot of the fool purgative for each
of them you have a shortage of the
identify and is there any limit on the
number of nodes of a directory or is
that down to the file system
there is no limit whatsoever that is
imposed by the standard so you can apply
this construction to any kind of option
and by the way if you are curious
one of our Engineers who actually
finishes his PhD thesis and now moved to
Google research and 23 under the
direction of our Stephen of zakiradi who
is a brilliant research in our team they
actually did the study of the shape of
this graph and then you discovered that
for example of course the the nodes that
correspond to commits and releases
televisions they can create change which
are extremely long so imagine that the
Linus kernel has millions of commits so
you have a long long long long chain
like this that is not actually no limit
on the number of the depth of this thing
on the other side in the directory part
it is kind of unbounded also in the
graph you have places where you have
tens of thousands of files in the same
direction and we all represent the same
thing in exactly the same way it just
gets up with the harsh as you mentioned
we often think about hashes when we talk
about password hashes and how the the
new recommendation comes comes out to
use this format and that type of hash
when you're talking about proving the
Integrity of a file you mentioned sha1
somewhere there could be a potential of
a clash what type of hash do you use
well that's an interesting point first
of all a little remark on the theory
behind this okay so when you do
cryptographic hashes of course there
will be conflict so there will be
objects that will end up having the same
hash for a very simple reason that the
input space of the hashing function is
much bigger than the output space of the
action interaction but when the number
of logic we are storing is much smaller
than the upper limit of the outer space
the big question is whether your hash
infaction is able to actually avoid a
random conflicts what is the probability
that you pick two different object at
random and they end up with the same
hash and for the historian cryptography
you have seen many many different
factors absorbing over time so we have
the crc32 that was just a small checks
on for from memories and then md5 that
ended up being useless when you have
tons of different files today then show
one was developed which was pretty safe
until a few years ago when Google
founded the project to actually
fabricate the two t75 with the same hash
and now people are moving to shot 256
etc etc it's a constant process this is
the reason why we had this number of
operation of the standard in in the
identifier remember the swh color one
for today now one
do they correspond to using exactly in
the same hashing function used by the
Git Version Control System this is a
show one only sorted version of the file
so you do not just compute the show one
on the file itself you compute someone
on the file has been prefixed by a
little bit of information that is
typically the type of the file the
length of the file
see that makes it more complicated to
have a harsh config but in the future we
plan to follow what the induces random
will be so it's a moment in time we will
need to move to a stronger hashing
function for the moment it is not
necessary but we are following what is
going on and eventually will provide a
version to version 3 for this identifier
standard to cope with the needs that we
develop over the time thank you and as I
understand the software Heritage ID is
the prefix anyway is registered with
Ayana so it is a standard yes well
actually the prefix it registry Diana
which is the first step then we have
there is a property in Wiki data that
correspond to some of the software
identifier there is an industry standard
which is spdx a software package data
exchange maintained by the Linux
Foundation that mentions the softwage
identifier static conversion 2.2 and
actually we are now in the process of
creating a real ISO standard work for
these identifiers that will take several
months of time where all the technical
precise detail or details on how the
identifiers are computed what is the
precise syntax that need to be used I
mean everything needed for anybody else
to rebuild their own system to compute
the social identifier for software they
have or what they have is underway and
if you're curious is there is a now a
website dedicated to this that is called
swh id.org
where if somebody who is technically
knowledgeable want to come in and lend a
hand participate in this standardization
the process is open to everybody you
just go to this website we'll see the
pointers to the current specification
which is undergoing review all the
information to join the team that works
together on improving the standard thank
you best take us on to wrapping up the
shirt that's been um really good just to
close off the section for the last
minute or so before we wrap up what was
the software Heritage ID before you know
what did you try before you got to that
when we started this we didn't have the
real clear idea what to use so before
starting the project we look at to other
identifiers for example in Academia that
is my word we are used to to identify
application using something which is
called the digital object identifier but
then we look at how these digital
identifier means design and we found
that it was not the right solution it is
an extreme secret identifier again it is
with the register Etc and you have no
guarantees of Integrity of the company
but we were already using regularly kit
and Courier and this kind of distributed
version control system without asking
ourselves how it works okay just using
it and then we decided to look into how
that was working and so we understood
the the underlying technology Etc and we
said okay this is a way of doing things
this exactly this the way of doing
things but then we don't want to be
stuck with one particular Version
Control System we want to have something
Universal that was a reason to actually
propose this identifiers as in
independent orthogonal approach to
identification or software source code
independently of the version control
system that you use so instead of saying
ah just put it in git and then get an
identify was not a solution for us we
needed to have something that will work
with software coming from where other is
it's something that happens time and
time again when you end up thinking
around the subject or or I do personally
where
you think this must have been invented
somewhere or in you somewhere else for
what I'm trying to solve let me go and
look at a different put a different
heart on think about the subject go for
a walk and then like you've just said
been using it and getting let's pull
that apart and so you have to apply it
for something else yes if you may add
something is it let's say we we are very
lucky up to now in this initiative
because if we had decided to start it 10
years earlier so instead of 2015 we have
decided to start in 2000 or something
had this 2002 2003. well this technology
would not have been available so we
would probably not have the idea of
using it and who knows what kind of mess
we would have made okay so we were kind
of Lucky on starting the project
sufficiently late to have access to the
right technology and then you remember
what we mentioned up here like for
example safe it was not available
sufficiently late to be able to build on
the shoulder of giants as well as every
good engineer should do and sufficiently
early to be present when the big big
Dentures arrived when when Google could
shut down when Italia shut down when a
big bucket removed the cryptominium
project we were already there and this
is the reason why we archived or that
and you can find it in the archive now
the big question is how long our good
start or our luck will will stay well it
also depends on on our reason today if
you find the project interesting have a
look at it you can contribute it is open
source and or if you work for big
companies that do not know it exists
tell them I mean if you want to support
an important common joint frame or
platform that can be useful well
probably software actually something you
should look at and and see how to join
this mission in this movement again you
see probably you have heard in this kind
of conversation how much passion we put
in this project this is the reason why
all the people put in the team actually
work overtime because they are
passionate about creating on this but it
is this what we are telling you about
it's not the end of the story it's not
even the beginning of the end of the
story okay it's it's a start or the
wrong Adventure where all of us in
particular us coming from computer
technology and computer science beard
responsibility of making this archive
exist in the runtime we often talk about
software engineering software
development being an art form you know
art and we need to protect art so that's
what we're doing here okay I think we've
done a great job of covering why the
software Heritage initiative exists
the challenges you've already faced and
the ones that are coming up and the
various stages of the techniques you've
developed to make it successful at the
moment but if there was one thing you'd
like a software engineer or one of our
listeners to remember from our show what
would you like that to be Roberto a
couple of things when what we are doing
I mean developing software is not just
tools it's much more I mean software is
a creation of human Ingenuity they need
to be recognized and the only way to
actually showcase it is to keep and show
the source code of the software we
develop I mean the quality work we are
doing day after day developing this kind
of technology is a form of artists kind
of clearly we made this clear in many
statement together with Eunice when you
remember when you work on software not
just for the money not just for the
technology it because you are
contributing to a part
of our Collective knowledge as humankind
today so that's essential and then
so this is not just a tragedy it's
software engineering and but then about
software Heritage well social Heritage
is an evolving infrastructure which is a
revolutionary infrastructure in the
service of research or a service of
industry or public administration or
cultural heritage and actually we need
you to help us building a better
infrastructure and make it more
sustainable then there are many use case
for industry we didn't have time cover
here but if you look at the archive you
will see there are probably many ideas
you will have on how to use this to
build better software thank you was
there anything we missed that you'd like
to mention before we close surely talk
too many things you know seven years in
a few dozens of minutes will be always
be something that we are missing but
maybe in a last moment you have seen the
rising worries about cyber security that
we are facing today
well this was not the original Mission
of soft Heritage but actually the
southwestern archive due to the way it
is built okay so if you've seen the
miracle trees a transic identifier the
duplication traceability of the contents
through the graph etc etc it's actually
providing a fantastic infrastructure to
help securing this open source software
supply chain so we are just again at the
beginning of this but next time you
build the project or you discuss with
people that ask questions like where
does this project come from can we trust
this particular project how can you
ensure it has not be tampered with Etc
it's nice to have in back of your mind
the fact that there is a place where
actually some people are building this
Universal very large telescope for
little dogs to look at the way software
is developed worldwide using
cryptographic identifier that lets you
actually track and check Integrity of
every single component contain a Terrain
yeah it could be that people prefer to
come and get the archive from software
Heritage of their own project rather
than trust it where they normally work
so it's a very good point where can
people find out more people can follow
you on Twitter but how else would you
like them to get in touch well there are
many ways of knowing more I mean you can
go to the main web pages with City
society.org look there there are
dedicated web pages for different people
so there is a web page for develop a
regular web page for user there are FAQs
and tons of informations there are
different links on how to use the
archive if you want to get a feed of
news on our Twitter feed is swh Heritage
search operator with SW at the beginning
and we had a newsletter that we have a
newsletter that goes out every three
four months so not not very
likely to to clog up your your remain
and you can subscribe and go into
software.org newsletter where we try to
summarize the news and provide you all
interest to the things that are
happening around and last but not least
as Gavin mentioned there is a growing
number of ambassadors that willing to
help spread the word about the project
and they they get direct access to the
team and help us explain to other what
this is on and creating a large
community what was what is happening so
you can contact them there on the web
page
tutorials ambassadors thanks a lot Kevin
for being one of the those Ambassador by
the way and so there is space for many
others and do not hesitate in contact
them if you want to learn more Roberto
thank you for coming on the show it's
been a real pleasure this is Gavin Henry
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening